that I'm just imagining that what you
just described again is the experience
of what happens when is the results or
when you feel securely attached to
yourself and another you have that depth
of experience where you're more I think
that you're more comfortable with the
unknown more able to tolerate conflict
and ambiguity and as you always talk
about that that's the measure of
satisfaction and intimacy is comfort
with anxiety because as you say we're
always going to be anxious with the
unknown and so we really that's
something you directed my attention to
is switching to my focus to pay
attention to how do I relate to my only
diary in relationship it's in a way of
me it's in the way of intimacy with
others I'm totally and that and directly
that how I understand that is the
paradox it could be human is to
simultaneously want to like have a deep
drive to realize my own kind of cosmic
specialness as a single as a single
individual and at the same time want to
merge with everything right first things
come together needs are met in one
single raishin ship if we're going to
get close it means on some level both
those things are what I want and so for
me to be me for me to be closer to you
and to become in a certain sense one
with you is analogous with me risking
being different than you right and
taking that risk which always includes
anxiety excitation courage and my
understanding of like how we how we move
away from anxiety which is circling you
could say is the practice of not moving
away from that anxiety and relaxed
intensity and actually moving towards it
and growing versus like submitting or
distributing or dominating the situation
all the different things that we do to
move away from that moment yeah for sure
one thing another so we have those those
six
and the seventh or seven and then the
last two are the Greuther clearings and
community and I ceramic people have
commented when they read what I wrote in
the first article about I'm imagining I
think what I'm hearing is they're taking
this theory that circling promotes the
experience of secure attachment and
they're overlaying the process of
psychotherapy on the circling and you
know and some people have suggested well
what happens if everyone in the circle
is if no one is securely attached what
happens if the facilitator isn't
securely attached and what I'm
suggesting is that doesn't matter it's
not as long as we understand the
agreements and our intention is to keep
listening keep owning our experience all
everything else we've talked about and
there's at least one person in a circle
who can facilitate and slow things down
we tend tell we almost always I mean
rarely have we not recovered from having
a certain kind of intensely occur and
what I'm noticing is so different from
circling and psychotherapy is circling
is not group therapy but it's very
therapeutic when you have five or six
people mirroring you to you instead of
just one person you can choose which one
feels right or maybe they all do and
often people reflect very different
things that all fit in some way but to
me there creates this holding
environment the way Winnicott would
describe the holding environment of the
mother and child and and and I think
that that is is fundamentally different
than group therapy where it could become
more there can be more confrontation
there's that's a very important practice
fundamentally but this is just something
very different about the way we're
relating yeah I think I just simply say
that the one thing that you said about
like you know what happens if everyone
including the facilitator is securely
attached like the girl line leading the
blind was kind of like you say that is
kind
like saying what happened if we all get
together and meditate and one of us has
a thought right well it's a little more
perplexing that goes through well I
think what it does is partially anyways
it points to like that that the
underlying presuppositions that are both
implicit and explicit encircling is the
structure that holds just like you're
you're talking about it creates kind of
a holding environment if you vote for it
for something like circling to happen
and so that's what's really cool about
and why if the practice right it's like
it's there's you could say rules the
game right and and just like any were
like you know if you change the rules of
Monopoly you'll have a different game
you know circling has some underlying
rules like owning your own experience
you know then throw other than attempt
those kinds of things yeah it's that we
don't have to be not nuts
in accent respect circles are where we
talked about like we always recover
where those experiences where people do
actually are forthcoming and share
dissonance maybe maybe like really well
and responsibly sometimes not so
responsibility but with the commitment
to just continually coming together
getting shared reality on experience
getting each others worlds being with
what so which is really what the
practice is is the practice is I like to
say sitting in the question how
profoundly can we be with what is right
and so if you think about just that like
imagine imagine imagine if you're if
you're with somebody and you're just
taking a walk right and you start
talking to them and really where they're
coming from is is is is is relating to
you from the question how profoundly can
I be with what is with you right now
this imagine that like how that walk
would be right because what kind of
conversations could come up what would
that feel like what kinds of things you
may talk about what kinds of silences
you may have but I think that if we if
we all started to
to live in a world where that was more
of the come from in our relations in the
way that we were leading other than
communicating in order to get what I
want instead right relating in order in
if another is paying exquisite attention
right and then sharing what so with your
moment-by-moment with the intention to
relate and to be with what is I have a
feeling relationships really really
different and may even be very very
nourishing much more nourish the process
of actually getting to that point is
complex just if you just put out a list
of that as a rule book and people
studied on their own some people
couldn't do it but many can't and it was
something I even after studying
psychotherapy for two and a half decades
I still had to practice the sharing of
impact the revealing of experience on a
personal level is very challenging and
so so just because people might know and
hear the word you just said
you just can't you can't substitute the
framework for actually doing it and it
just requires experiencing over and over
and what I'm imagining is that circling
would be like homeopathy a homeopathic
experience for the six year attachment
where because people experience more
warmth and connection after we see it
every Monday night after three hours
people are from how they felt in the
beginning to the end of the evening is
she's consistently remarkably different
and but I'm imagining we can just do
that over and over and over and over and
over again this something starts to slip
in your nervous system so that's what
I'm suggesting people try oh yeah I
totally agree and if anything if
anything the experience of circling I
would say if anything it can begin to
set a precedence for what's possible and
it's like you know if you think about it
I've been thinking about this lately you
know me and my trip you thought that I
have but I've been thinking about like
the point
me before what before Columbus you know
that the world was round you know what
were people walking around talking about
how not round the earth was like were
they like having a relationship with
like like how unwound it was become kind
of thick they even called it round or
not round it just was I don't even know
if they thought of it as flat but I bet
that once word got out that that it went
all the way around as a feeling once
people realized that it was possible to
go west and end up back to where you
were that that was possible which set a
precedence for what what made every so
many other things possible and how
across the ocean how the horizon looked
and what meant to you so I think that
like these these deep experiences that
people have it circling if anything if
anything what it does is I think it set
the precedence for what's possible and
if you set a precedence for what's
possible it changes that like that it's
probably change in their horizon right
which is what gives meaning right so
it's like I just can't emphasize that
enough that even like even if you just
go once right and you have that
experience you know those kinds of
experiences do do have a big impact and
I think this early report yeah I
remember that you said that you use that
term the first time we were working
together and you use that over and over
and how much my horizon would change and
you are the one that gave me that that
visual and I like the way you're still
referring to that because it's I think
it's it's very profound well I will
always refer to it until I finally catch
it I mean I've been here four years and
I just well it won't think won't let me
sit well really fun to talk with you and
let's do it again sometime
much love it's so great thank you for
doing this work okay thank you I